Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ד, mem daled,
and believe it or not we are on מ"ד. mem daled. Three
lines from the top in the גמרא, Gemara, we had just read
the משנה Mishnah that spoke about if a four brothers and it
said they all died, but the גמרא's Gemara going to correct that.
Anyway, the number of them died or four died and there was
others that were alive. The oldest one still gets the right, opportunity,
privilege, however you define it of doing יבום yibum with all of
them, not just with the first one. So if he wants to,
he can do יבום yibum with all before the other brothers get
their say. And then it goes on to the issue about that
חליצה chalitzah or יבום yibum with one exempts the others, something we've
been assuming from the very beginning. And then finally, what if one
of them is already פסול לכהונה? pasul le-kehunah? So those are the
three cases. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Let's go to the משנה Mishnah for a second.
It says,
"Totally, a number of the משניות mishnayot in this מסכת masechet in
this פרק perek should have started the מסכת." masechet. ארבעה אחים סלקא
דעתך, arba achim salka daitach, four
only four brothers? If they all died, who's left to do יבום?
yibum? אלא אימא ארבעה מן האחים, ela eima arba me-achim, four of
the brothers died leaving four wives, and then there's another brother and
then there are a few other brothers. The oldest one gets the
opportunity to first to do יבום yibum with all of them. הרשות
בידו, ha-reshut beyado, he has the permission to to do יבום yibum
with all of them. ושבקינן ליה? ve-shavkinei? Would we allow him to
marry more than one wife? והתניא, ve-hatanya, we learned in the ברייתא,
baraita, וקראו לו זקני עירו. ve-karu lo ziknei iro. Now finally, we're
also getting to the question of like, you know, some of the
decisions involved or guidance involved in terms of doing יבום yibum or
חליצה. chalitzah. Again, one thing we have very much not heard about
was the woman's voice, although רש"י Rashi did bring it in earlier.
Here again, we're not exactly going to hear about the woman's voice,
but we're going to hear about like society or the leadership, the
voice of giving him some type of a guidance. וקראו לו זקני
עירו, ve-karu lo ziknei iro, the elders of the city shall call
him, הן ולא שלוחן, hen ve-lo sheluchan,
first of all, they themselves have to be in direct conversation with
him, not through an intermediary. ודברו אליו, ve-dibru eilav, and they shall
speak to him. מלמד שמשיאין לו עצה ההוגנת לו, melamed she-masiin lo
eitzah hogenes lo, what do they mean they speak to him? So,
you know, why don't it just say he goes and he does
this ritual? So there's obviously some conversation that precedes the ritual. So
the גמרא Gemara understands that this is about giving him direction and
guidance. מלמד שמשיאין לו עצה ההוגנת לו, melamed she-masiin lo eitzah hogenes
lo, you give him a good
advice, ההוגנת לו, hogenes lo, appropriate for him. אם היה הוא ילד
והיא זקנה, im hayah hu yeled ve-hi zekeinah, if he was young
and the sister-in-law was elderly, או הוא זקן והיא ילדה, o hu
zaken ve-hi yaldah,
or he was elderly and she was young, אומרים לו, omrim lo,
you say to him, "מה לך אצל ילדה?" mah lecha etzel yaldah?
What do you want to do marrying such a young woman? Or,
"מה לך אצל זקנה?" mah lecha etzel zekeinah? What do you a
young man want to do marrying such an old woman? כלך אצל
שכמותך, kelech etzel she-kamotecha, go marry somebody of your own age, ואל
תשים קטטה בביתך, ve-al tasim ketatah be-veitecha, do not make a fight
in your house. You know, what do you want with this type
of a marriage? It's only going to lead to bad things. So
again, interesting, because they're the ones giving him this advice. A, he's
free to reject it, and also B, it doesn't speak about her
own opinion, which again was something that we will see later. So
the relevance here, though, is what's he doing marrying four women, four
co-wives, plus maybe he's already married to a wife? Isn't that going
to be pretty challenging to have all those wives? And especially, you
know, even in societies that were polygamous like בבל, Bavel, you know,
it would really only be the wealthy men that could afford to
have multiple wives. One minute, so what's the answer? So the גמרא
Gemara says, לא צריכא דאפשר ליה, lo tzericha de-efshar lei,
so the question is, how does the משנה Mishnah just start to
say he can marry all four? Why would why wouldn't we try
to to dissuade him of that? It's just a bad idea. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, it's a case where actually he's a
person of means and he can support multiple wives.
All around, same age, yeah,
that wasn't clear in the משנה, Mishnah, but the point was multiple
wives. אי הכי, i hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, and they're all
around the same way, yeah, that wasn't clear in the משנה, Mishnah,
but the point was multiple wives. אי הכי, i hachi, says the
גמרא, Gemara, אפילו טובא נמי, afilu tuvna nami, why does it limit
it only to four? Why not take twenty? So the גמרא Gemara
says, עצה טובה קא משמע לן, eitzah tovah ka mashma lan, no,
there already it's good advice, even if he is a person of
means, ארבע אין טפי לא, arba in tfeih lo, four wives, more
not, assuming he's not married to any if any before, right? כי
היכי דתמטי עונה בחודש, ki heichi de-timtei onah be-chodesh, if a very
if it's
if he's a person of the profession like a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham or other profession that normally the מצווה mitzvah of עונה's onah
once a week. So if he's got four wives, so, you know,
you divide the עונה onah by the number of wives. So therefore,
it would he would be with he would be once a week
he'd be having sex, but the wives would be on a rotation,
so he'd only have sex with one oh yeah, whatever, you'd only
have sex with a wife once a month, but less than once
a month would not be a good idea for him or for
them. I mean, he's doing it once a week, but for them,
anyway, so therefore more than five four wives is already a bad
idea. Good to know. You know, it's interesting that the Muslims limit
to four wives because Mohammed had no more than only had four
wives. So even though and even in Muslim countries where polygamy
is ex I was once in Senegal on a whatever you know
like a
rabbinic mission or something, and we had a and they like 98%
of the people there are polygamists. It's like only 2% of the
Christian population and monogamous. And this was with some rabbinical students from
different seminaries anyway. So like you could see everybody was trying to
get their head around the fact that like you know they they'd
heard about it in theory, but actually like see a really polygamist
society and see when you go to the villages you sort of
see like the story of like אברהם יצחק יעקב. Avraham Yitzchak Yaakov.
Like you know there's these little compounds and the women have like
their separate you know their separate rooms or whatever you know like
huts or whatever and you know and the person and they're like
on a rotation and then when one you know taking turns of
watching the kids or of doing different you know different roles within
the family anyway. So we had a conversation once with a group
of women. It was not about this at all. It was about
education in the community in the society. Anyway one of the students
sort of says like so what's it like like you know being
a you know you know being in a polygamous society? So of
course they were like a little bit dumbfounded because they didn't know
what like how would you respond to that question? Like what's it
like being monogamous? You know? So there was like this uneasy silence.
I decided I'm going to wisely or unwisely jump in with a
joke and this was all being translated. So I said, so I
said, so I said, so I said to them, and it's always
a risk doing humor cross culture anyway. So I said, I said,
so I said, so what is the you know you know you
know what's the penalty for polygamy? So they said to like whatever
so you know so the person translated the question and then it
was like whatever and then I said so two mother-in-laws. So then
you saw like this pause and like you know translating and then
like they crack up like they say hilarious like you know obviously
mother-in-law humor does translate across culture. And then one woman stands up
and she like shakes her head and she says.
So there you go. That was a society with four wives, yeah.
It's interesting here the same that הקרובות ha-keruvot dissuaded him but then
in the actual flow of פסוקים pesukim it's to persuade him because
like he's
supposed to do it and then if he doesn't want to I
understand.
Right, that's how חז"ל Chazal read it. Okay. So give him the
whatever advice is most appropriate.
He
yelled
at or he can versus him. I mean this is a society
where men much much older would marry someone younger. Right, so that's
an... right, or or you see how that as society evolves what
עצה הגונה eitza hogenes might change based on the norms of the
society even if it's not true in terms of the תורה Torah
society that was being referred to. Okay. So now it says מי
שהיה נשוי. mi she-haya nasuy. So now it says that ייבום yibbum
or חליצה chalitzah with any one wife exempts the others. So where
do you know this from? I mean this is what we've been
assuming from day one but where do you know this from from
the verses? וייבם לתרייהו v'yeyavem l'treiyahu how do you know you can't
do ייבום yibbum with both wives? Again some of these verses we've
quoted before, we're reviewing it. אמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא אמר רבי
יוחנן אמר קרא,
Amar Rabbi Chama berabi Chanina amar Rabbi Yochanan
amar kra, the verse says אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו, asher
lo yivneh et beit achiv, like this is what will be done
to the person who will not build his brother's house. בית אחד
הוא בונה, bayis echad hu boneh, so you see what's up for
is building one house. ואין בונה שני בתים, v'ein boneh shenei batim,
not two houses. And a wife is considered like the בית, bayis,
so therefore you can only do ייבום yibbum with one with one
wife.
That's a strange observation because the brother had a house, also had...
right, that's true, that's true, that's true. His בית bayis consisted of
two wives. ונחלוץ לתרייהו, v'nechalos l'treiyahu, and it's also interesting again that
the woman is the בית bayis even though the man is defines
the family unit, right, as the head of the household, the woman
is the בית, bayis, right? ביתו זו אשתו, beito zu ishto, a
very common trope in the גמרא. Gemara. ונחלוץ לתרייהו, v'nechalos l'treiyahu,
so okay how do you know if he wants to do חליצה
chalitzah he doesn't have to do חליצה chalitzah with both? How do
you know חליצה chalitzah with one exempts the others? אמר מר זוטרא
בר טוביה אמר קרא, Amar Mar Zutra bar Tuvia amar kra, בית
חלוץ הנעל, beit chalutz hana'al, they will call him the house of
the withdrawn shoe, of the removed shoe. בית אחד הוא חולץ, bayis
echad hu choletz, again בית bayis understood to mean in terms of
the wife, he only does חליצה chalitzah with one בית bayis ואין
חולץ שני בתים, v'ein choletz shenei batim, not two. וייבם לחדא ונחלוץ
לחדא, v'yeyavem l'chada v'nechalos l'chada,
okay how do you know maybe if he does ייבום yibbum with
one he shouldn't do חליצה chalitzah with the other? Okay maybe he
doesn't have an option of doing two חליצות chalitzot or two ייבומים
yibbumim but maybe he should do one חליצה chalitzah and one ייבום
yibbum assuming there's only two wives. What if there's more than two
wives? I don't know. It's a very funny question because but let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answers. אמר קרא Amar kra אם לא
יחפוץ im lo yachpotz if he doesn't want to do ייבום yibbum
then he does חליצה. chalitzah. הא אם חפץ יבם ha im chafetz
yavam and if he wants to do ייבום yibbum he does ייבום
yibbum and he doesn't do חליצה. chalitzah. כל העולה לייבום עולה
לחליצה, kol ha-oleh l'yibbum oleh l'chalitzah, anybody who ייבום yibbum was possible
you do חליצה. chalitzah. וכל שאינו עולה לייבום v'kol she-eino oleh l'yibbum
and the second wife who now we've already determined you can't have
do ייבום yibbum with, אינו עולה לחליצה, eino oleh l'chalitzah, doesn't have
חליצה. chalitzah. ועוד, v'od, so that's a very good reason and then
it says a very strange reason, a rabbinic reason after explaining it
at a biblical level, maybe to answer the question why not do
it rabbinically anyway, שלא יאמרו בית מקצתו בנוי ומקצתו חלוץ, she-lo yomru
bayis miktzaso banuy u-miktzaso chalutz, and let's
because people shouldn't think that you can do ייבום yibbum with half
the house and חליצה chalitzah with the other. Oh, that's a little
circular. Why is it a problem for people to think that? ויאמרו,
v'yomru, let them say that. אי דמייבם והדר חליץ, ee d'm'yavem v'hadar
chalitz, הכי נמי, hachi nami, fine. If everybody wants to do first
יבום yibbum and then חליצה, chalitzah, nothing bad'll come out of it.
But אלא, ella, הכי נמי, hachi nami, אלא דילמא חליץ והדר מייבם.
ella dilma chalitz v'hadar m'yavem.
The problem is is that if people see יבום yibbum and then
חליצה, chalitzah, they'll start doing חליצה chalitzah and then יבום. yibbum. דקאי
בלא יבנה. d'ka'i b'lo yivneh.
And once he did חליצה chalitzah with one wife, he's not allowed
to do יבום yibbum with the other wife. It's the prohibition of
אשר לא יבנה, asher lo yivneh, כיון שלא בנה שוב לא יבנה.
keivan shelo banah shuv lo yivneh. So anyway, biblically it's clear you
only do either יבום yibbum or חליצה. chalitzah. But then we're also
answering the strange question, which is why not rabbinically do both, which
is a pretty strange question. Why should you? But anyway the answer
is that it'll lead to trouble. Okay. ואימא כי איכא חדא תתקיים
מצות יבום, v'eima ki ika chada titkayem mitzvas yibbum, since it's all
about the singular בית חלוץ הנעל, beis chalutz ha-na'al, יבנה בית אחיו.
yivneh beis achiv.
So why don't we say when there's one wife, then you do
the מצות יבום? mitzvas yibbum? וכי איכא תרתי לא תתקיים מצות יבום.
v'ki ika tarti lo titkayem mitzvas yibbum.
If there are two wives, you don't do יבום. yibbum. Maybe the
whole thing takes place with one wife because it's all in the
singular. So the גמרא Gemara says this is a very funny הוה
אמינא. hava amina. Yeah, maybe walk away, or whatever. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, אם כן צרת ערוה דאסר רחמנא למה לי? im
kein tzaras ervah d'asar rachmana lamah lee? Why would what would we
have done with the first פרק? perek? Why would you have needed
the צרה tzarah to prohibit צרת ערוה, tzaras ervah, you know, if
because you're saying that anytime there are two wives you walk away,
so there's no whole discussion of צרת ערוה? tzaras ervah? השתא ביש
בעלמא אמרת לאו בני חליצה ויבום נינהו? hashta beis b'alma amart lav
bnei chalitzah v'yibbum ninhu? If
just two wives, there's no obligation, צרת ערוה מבעיא? tzaras ervah mibaya?
Of course it wouldn't be an obligation if one of them is
an ערוה. ervah. So the גמרא Gemara says אלמה לא? almah lo?
Maybe no. Maybe there would have been an obligation in that case.
איצטריך, itztirich, I need to tell me that. סלקא דעתך אמינא ערוה
אבראי קיימא, salka daitach amina ervah abara'i kaima, maybe if one of
them is an ערוה, ervah, one of them is your sister, so
she doesn't count. She's not even in the discussion. She's on the
out. Right, she's on the outside. ערוה אבראי קיימא, ervah abara'i kaima,
thank you,
ותתיבם צרתה, v'tisyavem tzarasah,
and there should still be יבום yibbum with the co-wife. וקמשמע לן
דאסירא, v'kamashma lan d'asira,
that's why it's telling you it's forbidden. But maybe that works perfectly
with the idea that there's only יבום yibbum with one wife and
that's why you need צרת ערוה tzaras ervah to tell me that
don't consider it like one wife or consider it one wife but
there's a צרה, tzarah, whatever. Anyway, וקמשמע לן דאסירא. v'kamashma lan d'asira.
אלא, ella, so how do you know it's even applies with more
than one wife? יבמתו יבמתו ריבה yevimto yevimto ribah because it says
יבמתו yevimto multiple times. יבמתו יבמתו yevimto yevimto tells you that it
could even be when there are two sister-in-laws. Okay, that's where we
get the idea that even though there are multiple co-wives, you only
do יבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah with one. The man only does
יבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah with one. היתה אחת כשרה. hayisa achas
k'sheirah. If one was כשרה k'sheirah and one was פסולה, psulah, פסול
psul not being ערוה ervah because then it wouldn't be relevant, but
if one was basically, what do you call it, if one was
let's say already a גרושה grushah from a previous marriage. So it
says if you're going to do חליצה, chalitzah, do חליצה chalitzah with
the גרושה grushah so you don't make the one who's the who's
an אלמנה almanah invalid to a כהן. kohen. Why why make her
status problematic? If you're going to however do יבום, yibbum, it says
you do יבום yibbum with the כשרה. k'sheirah. Now it doesn't mean
דווקא davka the כשרה. k'sheirah. The רמב"ם Rambam for example says if
you're going to do יבום, yibbum, do יבום yibbum with whichever one
you want. Okay, but it means even the כשרה. k'sheirah. But if
you're going to do חליצה, chalitzah, do it with the פסולה. psulah.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יוסף כאן שנה רבי, amar
Rav Yosef kan shanah Rebbi, here Rebbi taught לא ישפוך אדם מי
בורו, lo yishpoch adam mei boro, don't spill out the water of
your well ואחרים צריכים להם, v'acherim tzrichim lahem, and other people need
it. Like
don't waste something. Oh, well you know, what do I care? No
difference to me. Very nice, no difference to you, please take other
people into consideration. Okay, so if you're going to do חליצה, chalitzah,
do it with the woman who already has a פסול psul status
to a כהן. kohen.
משנה. Mishnah. Yes.
So the conclusion there is you presumably if there were four and
four, one brother could take all four the wives. Correct. That's separate
from the idea of doing יבום yibbum with only...
Yes, because they're four different for two four different brothers. Correct. The
idea of one for many is when they're all from the same
brother.
רבנן, Rabbanan, how do you read the line כל העולה ליבום עולה
לחליצה וכל שאינו ליבום אינו לחליצה? kol ha'oleh l'yibbum oleh l'chalitzah v'chol
she'eino l'yibbum eino l'chalitzah?
Anybody who's יבום yibbum is possible, you have to do חליצה. chalitzah.
Anybody for whom יבום yibbum is not possible, חליצה chalitzah is not
relevant either.
So the second wife who you can't do יבום yibbum with because
we already said בית אחד הוא בונה, bayis echad hu boneh, you
can't also do חליצה chalitzah with. Okay. המחזיר גרושתו. hamachzir grushaso. Now
somebody who now we get into another shift of conversation after finally
at the end of all the יבום yibbum discussions getting the משנה
Mishnah we should have started with, we now start talking about issues
about personal status and as I said sadly the next few days
when I'm gone is going to be all the סוגיות sugyas about
גירות, geirus, but you know the issues about personal status, גירות geirus
is a big discussion and ממזר mamzer is a big discussion about
if you're allowed, you know what relevant personal status that's not sort
of just and also you know all the issues about פסול לכהונה.
psul l'kehunar. These are all the different types of different statuses that
are very relevant to מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamot. So you see, so
so we now get to the discussion begin the discussion of ערוה
araya of of ממזר. mamzer. Let's take a look. המחזיר גרושתו, hamachzir
grushaso, a man who remarries the woman that he divorced after she
had married another man, which is a negative prohibition in the Torah.
But no... of different statuses that are very relevant to מסכת יבמות.
Masechet Yevamos. So you see, so we now get to this discussion,
begin the discussion of ערווה, erva, of ממזר. mamzer. Let's take a
look. המחזיר גרושתו, Hamachzir gerushaso, a man who remarries the woman that
he divorced after she had married another man, which is a negative
prohibition in the Torah. But nobody would ever call it an עריות.
arayos. והנושא חלוצתו, Vehonosei chalutzaso, or a man who marries a woman
he did חליצה chalitza with. Now that is a problem about, right,
about כיון שבנה שוב לא יבנה. kevan shebanah shuv lo yivneh.
Okay, but it's a simple negative prohibition. It's not considered brother's wife.
That doesn't matter if she married somebody else in the meantime.
Correct. Even without her being the, right, exactly, because that's just כיון
שבנה שוב לא יבנה kevan shebanah shuv lo yivneh even if she
didn't marry somebody else. והנושא קרובת חלוצתו. Vehonosei krovos chalutzaso. Now
this sounds purely rabbinic. The relative of his חלוצה chalutza like his
חלוצה chalutza sister. So remember we had that before, but that seemed
to be rabbinic, the same way you can't marry, a man can't
marry his divorced wife's sister because he can't marry his חלוצה chalutza
sister. Or he can't marry his divorced wife's mother, he can't marry
his חלוצה chalutza mother. But presumably that was because rabbinically we view
the woman who is a חלוצה chalutza as if she was his
wife and as if she's now his divorced wife. So any עריות
arayos that apply to wife apply to her. But that seems to
be rabbinic. So the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss that. So
the הלכה halacha is יוציא והולד ממזר, yotzi vehavalad mamzer, דברי רבי
עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you have to
get divorced and the child is a ממזר. mamzer. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva has a very strict opinion about ממזר. mamzer. Any offspring from
any prohibited relationship,
even a simple לאו, lav, even a man with the woman he
used to be married to, absolutely no relationship to any, you know,
no sense of, of incest or anything like that, or even חלוצתו,
chalutzaso, all these cases the child is a ממזר. mamzer.
Not from נדה. niddah.
Not from נדה, niddah, correct. והנושא חלוצתו וקרובתה? Vehonosei chalutzaso ukrovosah?
Yes, חלוצתו, chalutzaso, well not ערווה, erva, oh you mean because אשת
אחיו? eishess achiv? No, so the גמרא Gemara said that before. There
was some question about the other co-wives but because based on the
פסוק pasuk about כיון שבנה שוב לא יבנה kevan shebanah shuv lo
yivneh basically said that it's only a לאו, lav, it doesn't go
back to being אשת אחיו. eishess achiv.
And חלוצתו chalutzaso is relevant only if she married someone else and
then divorced that person?
Correct, even without her being, right, exactly. חכמים אומרים אין הולד ממזר.
Chachamim omrim ein havalad mamzer. No, the child is not a ממזר,
mamzer, that's going to be our position. Child is only a ממזר
mamzer if it results from an איסור כרת issur kares and not
נדה. niddah. ומודים בנושא קרובת גרושתו, Umodim benosei krovos gerushaso,
but they do concede that if a man marries the relative of
a woman he's, who's really a גרושה grusha to him, his ex-wife,
so let's say her sister, her daughter, her mother, in all those
cases שהולד ממזר, shehavalad mamzer, child is a ממזר mamzer because all
the prohibitions relating to relatives of one's wife, of a man's wife,
is not only when one is married to that woman, even after
one is divorced, even if a man is divorced from the wife,
all of those prohibitions remain. The only prohibition that changes is if
she dies, no, right, the only prohibition that changes is if she
dies and they're only related to her sister. So that's the only
difference. If she dies, then the sister is not prohibited. But the
other prohibitions, mother, daughter or whatever, all of those remain. So again,
after divorce they all remain, after death only the, the only one
that changes is wife's sister. Okay, so there they do concede that
is a real עריות. arayos. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. וסבר רבי עקיבא, Vsavar Rabbi Akiva, הנושא קרובת חלוצתו ולד ממזר?
hanosei krovos chalutzaso valad mamzer? Does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva really hold
the relative of a woman that he did חליצה chalitza with is
the child is a ממזר? mamzer? I mean presumably that's only rabbinic.
We've been assuming that the status of חלוצה chalutza to be like
an ex-wife, it's one thing maybe vis-a-vis a כהן, Kohen, maybe that
that would be a different status, but to make the relatives forbidden
like an ex-wife, that's דרבנן. derabbanan. ואמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Ve'amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, כאן שנה רבי, kan shanah Rebbe, here רבי
Rebbe taught, אחות גרושה מדברי תורה אחות חלוצה מדברי סופרים, achose gerusha
midivrei Torah achose chalutza midivrei sofrim,
the sister of a גרושה grusha is biblical, the sister of a
חלוצה chalutza is rabbinic. Right? That was based on an earlier משנה.
mishna. We're assuming רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does not disagree with that.
So assuming רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees with that, we're going to
switch the text. Fine. תני קרובת גרושתו, Tani krovos gerushaso, switch the
text. It should have said he didn't mean the relative of חלוצה,
chalutza, he meant the relative of a גרושה, grusha, of a woman
who really was this man's wife. That's הולד ממזר. havalad mamzer. Of
course that even the חכמים Chachamim agree to.
So the
גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra,
that makes sense, דקתני סיפא, dekatani seifa, because that's what the חכמים
Chachamim concede to in the end, ומודים בנושא קרובת גרושתו שהולד ממזר,
umodim benosei krovos gerushaso shehavalad mamzer, חכמים Chachamim concede that the relative
of a woman that the man divorced is the child is a
ממזר. mamzer. אי אמרת בשלמא איירי בה, Ei amart bishlama ayiri bah,
if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was talking about that case, that was
one of his cases, היינו דקתני ומודים, hainu dekatani umodim, then we
say okay, the rabbis disagree with two cases but they concede the
third one about the relative of a גרושה. grusha. אלא אי אמרת
לא איירי בה, Ella ei amart lo ayiri bah, if רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva wasn't even talking about it, if he was just talking
about קרובת חלוצתו, krovos chalutzaso,
so מאי ומודים, mai umodim, what do you mean they concede that
case? We weren't even discussing it for them to concede it. Of
course that's a pretty funny question because it was obviously a related
case, but okay. ודילמא, Vedilema, the גמרא Gemara says, הא קמשמע לן
דיש ממזר מחייבי כריתות, ha kamashma lan d'yesh mamzer mechayvei krisos,
maybe what it means they concede is it means that they're not
denying that there's, you know, that a ממזר mamzer is an offspring
of a forbidden relationship. They're just saying they'll concede cases of כרת,
kares, they won't concede cases of לאו, lav, but maybe we're not
you know. So it doesn't mean that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva specifically
talked about קרובת גרושתו. kerovas gerushaso. They're conceding, while we disagree with
all those three cases, we concede other cases are a ממזר. mamzer.
So the גמרא Gemara said הכי תני לה לקמן, hachi sani lah
le-kaman, no,
because that they just tell me that, that's taught later. איזו ממזר
כל שאר בשר, eizu mamzer kol sha'er basar,
what's a ממזר? mamzer? Any sort of offspring of an incestuous relationship.
שאר בשר sha'er basar means like you're related to the person. שהוא
בלא יבוא, shehu be-lo yavo, that is a negative prohibition. דברי רבי
עקיבא, divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said. Actually
שאר בשר sha'er basar according to that isn't limited to related because
it would even apply to like חלוצתו chalutzaso or ex-wife. Normally though
שאר בשר sha'er basar means that you're actually, you actually have a
familial relationship. Anyway, רבי שמעון התמני אומר, Rabbi Shimon Hatimoni omer, כל
שחייבים כריתות בידי שמים, kol she-chayavim kerisos bi-yedei shamayim,
anything that's a חייב כרת, chayav kareis, not anything that's a simple
לאו. lav. הלכה כדברי הרבים, halacha ke-divrei ha-rabim, we rule like him.
So anyway, if all they were doing was conceding, was saying, "Oh,
you say לאו lav and we say כרת," kareis, that's already in
a later משנה. mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא כדתני לה
לקמן כתנא דחכמים, ve-dilma ke-dtani lah le-kaman ke-tana de-Chachamim, so what it's
a later משנה? mishna? Here we're having the anonymous opinion, the חכמים,
Chachamim, the majority voice expressing that opinion. You רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
say לאו, lav, we say no, כרת, kareis, we'll agree with the
relative of a wife but nothing else or ex-wife. אם כן, im
kein, says the גמרא, Gemara, לתני שאר חייבי כריתות. lisni she'ar chayavei
kerisos.
If all they wanted to do was say, "You're talking about לאוין
lavin but we say it's only by כרת," kareis, why pick specifically
ex-wife's relative? Just give a normal example of a חייב כרת. chayav
kareis. קרובת גרושתו למה לי, kerovas gerushaso lamah li, why specifically pick
that? אלא שמע מינה איירי בה, ela shema mina airy bah, it
must be that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva himself mentioned it, and since
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva himself mentioned relative of an ex-wife, they said,
"Okay, that case we concede." So in order to explain why did
the חכמים Chachamim pick out of all the cases, you know, ex-wife's
relative, why not just stam say, "Well, you know, we concede it's
ממזר mamzer by חייב כרת," chayav kareis, it must have picked it
out because that must have been one of the three cases רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was talking about and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
not talking about the relative of a חלוצה. chalutza. All right. So
the גמרא Gemara says, well, that's a pretty weak argument because רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva could be talking about a relative of a חלוצה
chalutza and they could be saying while we disagree with a חלוצה,
chalutza, we agree with a גרושה, grusha, right? So there's really it's
really hard to prove from this that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
talking only about a גרושה. grusha. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא
לעולם לא איירי בה, ve-dilma le-olam lo airy bah, and that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. Maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was not talking
about a גרושה grusha case.
דאיידי דתנא מחזיר גרושתו ונושא חלוצתו וקרובת חלוצתו, de-aidi de-tana machzir gerushaso
ve-nosei chalutzaso ve-kerovas chalutzaso, you know, he's talking about everything right around
it. He said remarrying a divorcee,
marrying a חלוצה, chalutza, the relative of a חלוצה, chalutza, so you
got relatives and divorcees and חלוצות, chalutzos, so the one case that
he didn't mention was the relative of a גרושה. grusha. So they
say those three we disagree but the relative of a גרושה, grusha,
that we agree. תני נמי קרובת גרושתו. tani nami kerovas gerushaso. Okay.
So that's clearly פשט pshat in the משנה. mishna. פשט pshat in
the משנה mishna is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is genuinely talking about
קרובת חלוצתו kerovas chalutzaso and they're saying while we disagree with those
cases because those are all לאוין lavin or קרובת חלוצתו kerovas chalutzaso
might be rabbinic, we are going to say by קרובת גרושתו kerovas
gerushaso that is דאורייתא de-Oraisa and that's a כרת kareis even though
the man is no longer married to this woman and therefore that
case it is a ממזר. mamzer. Okay.
It would open up the possibility of a category of ממזר דרבנן.
mamzer de-Rabbanan. Right.
So it could have suggested that, that maybe according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva it's a ממזר דרבנן, mamzer de-Rabbanan, but let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes. Okay. ממזר דרבנן mamzer de-Rabbanan we'd rather not
have, we have enough problems with ממזר דאורייתא. mamzer de-Oraisa. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא קרובת חלוצתו לרבי עקיבא הוי ממזר. ela kerovas
chalutzaso le-Rabbi Akiva havei mamzer. אלא קרובת חלוצתו לרבי עקיבא הוי ממזר,
ela kerovas chalutzaso le-Rabbi Akiva havei mamzer, but maybe אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami, the relative of a חלוצה chalutza for רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva really is a ממזר mamzer even though we've been assuming
that that's only a rabbinic status. Maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
it's a biblical one. So is that really true? So אמר רבי
חייא בר אבין אמר רבי יוחנן היינו טעמא דרבי עקיבא. amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Avin amar Rabbi Yochanan hayinu taama de-Rabbi Akiva. Let me
explain to you רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva reasoning. דאמר קרא בית חלוץ
הנעל,
de-amar kra beis
chalutz ha-na'al, the תורה Torah says the house of the withdrawn shoe.
הכתוב קראו בית. ha-kasav kra'o bayis. Yes,
the תורה Torah calls this your house, your, so yes, this idea
that the woman the man did חליצה chalitza to is considered like
the man's ex-wife, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would actually say is דאורייתא.
de-Oraisa. So yes, it's true, רבי Rebbi has taught that a חלוצה
chalutza is rabbinic and the relative of a חלוצה chalutza is rabbinic
and that's everything we've been assuming, but guess what, in this משנה
mishna you find out that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva assumes that the
relative of a חלוצה chalutza is דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, that a woman a
man did חליצה chalitza to is like a woman he was married
to, is like a גרושה grusha for all biblical laws. Okay. So
quite fascinating. That is what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. אין הכי
נמי קרובת חלוצתו ein hachi nami kerovas chalutzaso is דאורייתא. de-Oraisa.
אמר רב יוסף. amar Rav Yosef. So now we've established that. Good
thing we don't rule like
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אמר רב יוסף אמר רב שמעון בר אבא.
amar Rav Yosef amar Rav
Shimon bar Abba.
אמר רב שמעון בר
אבא,
amar Rav Shimon
bar
Abba, I think.
Okay. הכל מודים. ha-kol modim. אמר רב שמעון בר רבי, Amar Rav
Shimon bar Rebbe, הכל מודים במחזיר גרושתו, hakol modim b'machzir grushaso, and
רב שמעון בר רבי Rav Shimon bar Rebbe says everybody agrees in
the case of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. Okay, so now we’ve got
the basic debate. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the child of a
חייבי לאוין chaivei lavin is a ממזר. mamzer. חכמים Chachamim say only
the child of a חייבי כריתות. chaivei krisos. And that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva also goes so far to say even the case of
relatives of a חלוצה chalutza is a ממזר. mamzer. Now we’re going
to get to the חכמים, Chachamim, the way you פסקן, pasken, so
pay attention, because here, even within the חכמים Chachamim that limit it
to the child of a חייב כריתות, chaiv krisos, maybe there are
other cases that are also problematic, except not to the same degree.
So everybody agrees that the child of a מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushaso,
which is only an איסור לאו, issur lav, a man who remarried
the woman he was he divorced after she married somebody else, שהולד
פגום לכהונה. she’havlad pagum l'kehuna. Even though the child is not a
ממזר, mamzer, he would be invalid to כהונה, kehuna, which means that
if it the child were a girl, she would be a she
would not be able to marry a כהן. kohen. If the child
were a boy, obviously he would not he would not have קדושת
כהונה kedushas kehuna because he’d be the child of a כהן kohen
and a גרושה, grusha, right? Child of a כהן kohen and a
גרושה grusha doesn’t even have to be מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushaso, is
a חלל, chalal, loses his קדושת כהונה. kedushas kehuna. But even if
the child is a girl and the father did no איסור, issur,
oh he did the איסור, issur, excuse me, did the איסור issur
of מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushaso,
the child although not a ממזר, mamzer, this girl cannot marry a
כהן. kohen. Okay, so this is going to be an important question:
Is the offspring of a sexual act that is prohibited by a
לאו, lav, although not a ממזר, mamzer, אסור assur to a כהן?
kohen? And that really would create a broad a lot of serious
implications, the biggest one being nowadays, what we’re going to get to,
not to ruin the surprise but to keep you interested, is the
case of a non-Jewish father and a Jewish mother. Is the child
who’s completely Jewish and not a ממזר, mamzer, although we saw before
there was an opinion ממזר mamzer you might remember, is the child
is the girl מותרת mutteres to marry a כהן? kohen? So let's
take a look. שהולד פגום לכהונה, she’havlad pagum l'kehuna, this child of
this prohibition of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. מאן
הכל מודים? Man hakol modim? Who concedes this point? שמעון התימני. Shimon
HaTeimani. שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani who says it's only the offspring of
a כרת kares that's a ממזר. mamzer. אף על גב דאמר שמעון
התימני אין ממזר מחייבי לאוין, af al gav d'amar Shimon HaTeimani ein
mamzer m'chaivei lavin, although he says there's no ממזר mamzer from simple
negative prohibitions, נהי דממזר לא הוי, nehi d'mamzer lo havei, he's not
a ממזר, mamzer, פגום מי הוי? pagum mi havei? He still is
פגום pagum or she is פגום, pagum, she cannot marry כהנים. kohanim.
מנלן? Manlan? Now how do you know that? מקל וחומר מאלמנה. m'kal
v'chomer m'almana. We’ll make a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. ומה אלמנה לכהן
גדול שאין איסורה שוה בכל, u'mah almana l'kohen gadol she'ein issura shaveh
b'chol, the story of an אלמנה almana to a כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, her right, if a כהן גדול kohen gadol marries an אלמנה,
almana, then the child
then she becomes the act of sex with her which is forbidden
act of sex with a כהן, kohen, her a כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, but it’s in the category of כהן, kohen, so that makes
her a חללה, chalala, she now cannot marry another כהן kohen even
if the כהן גדול kohen gadol dies. And the child, the offspring
also becomes invalid to marry if she's a girl, to marry other
כהנים. kohanim. So if that’s a simple לאו lav and the offspring
is forbidden to marry other כהנים, kohanim, so maybe the same by
all offsprings
of איסורי לאו. issurei lav. So ומה אלמנה לכהן גדול, u'mah almana
l'kohen gadol, the case of an אלמנה almana for a כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, שאין איסורה שוה בכל, she'ein issura shaveh b'chol, it's not
a general prohibition, it only applies to one person, the כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. בנה פגום, bnah pagum, the child is like stigmatized, that's
a good word for פגום, pagum, and she can't marry כהנים, kohanim,
it's just the offspring of a simple לאו lav even a very
narrowly defined לאו. lav. זו שאסורה שוה בכל, zu she'asura shaveh b'chol,
this prohibition of remarrying a divorced wife after she married someone else
which is a universal prohibition, אינו דין שבנה פגום, eino din she'bnah
pagum, how much more so should the child be stigmatized, should be
פגום pagum and not allowed to marry a כהן, kohen, the offspring
of this negative prohibition. גמרא Gemara says no, איכא למפרך, ika l'mifrach,
you can challenge that. מה לאלמנה שכן היא עצמה מתחללת. mah l'almana
shekein hi atzma mischaleles. By the case of of the אלמנה, almana,
she herself becomes a חללה. chalala. Now here’s the important thing that
you have to understand, that in terms of people being invalid for
כהנים, kohanim,
there it uniquely happens or particularly happens
when the an the the prohibition that was violated was a prohibition
that's specific to כהנים. kohanim. So for example, a כהן kohen marries
an אלמנה, almana, a כהן גדול kohen gadol marries an אלמנה. almana.
The reason it’s interesting there is you can’t say it’s a גרושה
grusha because she’s already married to forbidden to all כהנים. kohanim. But
a כהן גדול kohen gadol marries an אלמנה almana who’s only אסורה
asura to a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Because that is a specific
כהן kohen prohibition, the woman now becomes forbidden to all כהנים, kohanim,
even if the husband dies and she’s an אלמנה, almana, the act
of doing an איסור כהונה, issur kehuna,
a sexual act that’s forbidden on כהנים kohanim makes her a חללה.
chalala. As opposed to, let’s take the case of מחזיר גרושתו, machzir
grushaso, a man remarried oh that wouldn’t be good, she’s already a
גרושה. grusha. Let’s take the case of what would be a good
case of another איסור לאו. issur lav. That would not be a
woman already forbidden to a כוהן. Kohen.
What's another איסור לאו issur lav that's not a woman already forbidden
to a כוהן? Kohen?
Right,
a כוהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, again. So you're back to a כוהן
גדול Kohen Gadol case. Anyway, so if there's some other prohibition that
is a simple negative prohibition that's not unique to a כוהן, Kohen,
the child is not a... you know, is not, the woman is
not אסורה לכהונה asura l'kehuna as a result, okay? And therefore, because
it's not a unique כוהן Kohen prohibition, so that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying. Yes, the child of an אלמנה לכוהן גדול almanah
l'Kohen Gadol is going to be אסור לכהונה asur l'kehuna because the
woman becomes אסורה לכהונה asura l'kehuna as a result of this act.
But in the case of a מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushato, the woman
doesn't become more אסור asur to כוהן. Kohen. Now, how could she
become more אסור asur to כוהן? Kohen? She's already a גרושה. grusha.
So Rashi and Tosafos say, well, for example, if she was a
בת כוהן, Bas Kohen, she's still entitled to eat תרומה, terumah, right?
If a woman becomes פסולה לכהונה, psula l'kehuna, then she would be
invalidated from eating תרומה terumah if she was like a בת כוהן.
Bas Kohen. This would not apply to this woman. So when you're
not dealing with a specific כוהן-related Kohen forbidden act of sex, the
woman does not become invalidated as a result. And since the woman
does not become invalidated or more invalidated as a result, the גמרא
Gemara says you can't assume that the child will become invalidated either.
Okay, so מה אלמנה שכן היא עצמה מתחללת, ma almanah she-ken hi
atzmah mischalleles, but the אלמנה almanah herself becomes a חללה chalalah and
therefore the child becomes invalidated to כוהנים. kohanim. But in the case
of מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushato, the woman anyway is already... can't marry
כוהנים, kohanim, but this act doesn't make her more forbidden, for example
like about eating תרומה, terumah, and therefore the child would not be
affected.
And not only that, we have a פסוק, posuk, it says היא
תועבה, hi to’eivah, the פסוק posuk says about a man who remarries
his ex-wife who married another man, תועבה היא, to'eivah hi, it is
an abomination. And the דרשה drasha is היא תועבה ואין בניה תועבים,
hi to'eivah v'ein baneha to'eivim, she is the תועבה, to’eivah, but not
her children, her children have no problematic status. We even have a
פסוק posuk that says that the children don't have a problematic status.
ועוד תניא, v'od tanyia, we've taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, המחזיר גרושתו
והנושא חלוצתו, hamachzir grushato v'hanoseh chalutzaso, a man who remarries his ex-wife
or marries his חלוצה, chalutza, that's another case about כעיר שבנה שוב
לא יבנה, k'ir she-banah shuv lo yivneh, simple negative prohibition, והנושא קרובת
חלוצתו, v'hanoseh krovas chalutzaso, or marries the relative of the חלוצה, chalutza,
these are all the three cases רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva talked about.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר, omer, אין לו בקידושין, ein lo bakiddushin,
קידושין kiddushin is not binding, right? The same way ממזר mamzer and
not binding קידושין kiddushin go together, which means that you don't even
need a גט, get, you just walk away, there's no קידושין kiddushin
at all, even a simple לאו lav prevents any קידושין kiddushin from
taking place. ואין צריכה הימנו גט, v'ein tzricha mimenu get, doesn't need
a גט, get, he just walks away. היא פסולה, hi psula, she
becomes now invalid to a כוהן Kohen because she's now had an...
for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he makes an איסור לאו issur lav
like an איסור כרת. issur kares. So the same way that the
act is not within the context of קידושין, kiddushin, the child is
going to be a ממזר, mamzer, that act of sex is also
going to make her אסורה asura to a כוהן. Kohen. וולדה פסול,
vlada pasul, and the child becomes invalid to כוהנים... kohanim... I mean,
it's more than invalid to כוהנים, kohanim, the child is a ממזר.
mamzer. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. וכופין אותו להוציא, v'kofi'in
oso l'hotzi, and you force a divorce, I mean for him it
has the full weight, even a simple לאו. lav. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim
omrim, and the Sages say, יש לו בקידושין, yesh lo bakiddushin,
no, the exact opposite, not the exact opposite, everything he says we
don't agree. First of all, קידושין kiddushin is binding, וצריכה הימנו גט,
v'tzricha mimenu get, if it's only a לאו, lav, if it was
a כרת kares we'd concede, but it's only a לאו, lav, so
קידושין kiddushin is binding, if she wants to walk away she needs
a גט. get. והיא כשרה, v'hi k'sheira,
she does not become invalid to a כוהן. Kohen. I mean some
of these cases she's already invalid, she's a גרושה, grusha, but not
more invalid, for example she could eat תרומה, terumah, it's not like
having a... sex in the context of an איסור כרת. issur kares.
וולדה כשר, uvlada kasher, and the child
is still valid. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so that's the
thing we're going to hone in on, the child is כשר. kasher.
So here you have the offspring of an איסור לאו issur lav
according to the חכמים, Chachamim, and we say the child is כשר.
kasher. So כשר kasher sounds like completely כשר, kasher, not just not
a ממזר, mamzer, but completely כשר. kasher. למאן, l'man, who do we
mean the child is כשר kasher for? לאו לכהונה? lav l'kehuna? Don't
we mean the child can even marry a כוהן Kohen even if
it's a girl? לא, לאו
לכהונה. lo, lav l'kehuna. No, maybe we just mean that the child
isn't a ממזר mamzer and she can marry another Jew, but not
that she can marry a כוהן. Kohen. גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי,
ee hachi, if that's true,
היא כשרה למאן? hi k'sheira l'man? When it says earlier that the
woman is
כשרה, k'sheira, who is she כשרה k'sheira for? אי לימא לקהל, ee
leima l'kahal, if you mean that the woman that he had sex
with can now marry another Jew, פשיטא, pshita, of course. We never
have a woman
who starts off okay that does a forbidden act of sex and
becomes אסורה asura to other Jews, right? You can have a forbidden
act of sex that makes the woman אסורה asura to a כוהן,
Kohen, but the only way somebody could be a ממזר mamzer is
to be the offspring of an act of forbidden sex. So when
we say she is כשרה... k'sheira... She, the woman, is כשר Kasher
and the child is כשר. Kasher. To say she's כשר Kasher only
makes sense in terms of כשר Kasher to a כהן. Kohen. It
would never have been a thought that she would be invalid to
other Jews. So similarly the child, presumably we mean כשר Kasher even
to a כהן. Kohen. So if we're talking about her, פשיטא משום
דזניה, Peshita Mishum De'Zanya, because she committed, she did a forbidden act
of sex, אסור לקהל, Assur L'Kahal, she should be forbidden to other
Jews? The only way somebody's forbidden to other Jews is by being
a ממזר Mamzer which is the offspring of a forbidden act. But
the woman never! So the only thing a woman could become invalid
through a forbidden act of sex is to a כהן. Kohen. So
if we say she's כשר, Kasher, it means she's כשר Kasher to
marry a כהן Kohen or to eat תרומה Terumah in another scenario.
אלא לאו לכהונה, Ela Lav L'Kehunah, it must mean that this forbidden
act of sex, since it was only a negative prohibition, not כרת,
Karet, did not invalidate her for כהונה Kehunah purposes. So ומדהיא לכהונה,
U'mide'hi L'Kehunah, so since it's saying that she's כשר Kasher for כהונה
Kehunah purposes, ולד נמי לכהונה, V'lad Nami L'Kehunah, the child also is
כשר Kasher for כהונה Kehunah purposes. So you see that the child,
the offspring of this forbidden act, even since it's a לאו, Lav,
is כשר לכהונה Kasher L'Kehunah because it says כשרה, Kashera,
כשר, Kasher, and presumably it's כשר Kasher the same way she's כשר.
Kasher. מידי איריא, Midi Irya, what is that a proof? הא כדאיתא
והא כדאיתא. Ha Kide'ita V'ha Kide'ita. Each one is in its context.
She's כשר Kasher for the things that she might have been פסול
Passul for, כהונה, Kehunah, and he's כשר Kasher for the things Rabbi
Akiva invalidated. Rabbi Akiva would have made him a ממזר. Mamzer. No,
he's not a ממזר. Mamzer. But it's not saying he's totally כשר.
Kasher.
הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi Nami Mistabra, that makes sense, says the גמרא,
Gemara, דקתני רישא, DeKatni Reisha, because look at what Rabbi Akiva says.
היא פסולה, Hi Pesula, she's invalid, which means לכהונה. L'Kehunah. This is
Rabbi Akiva that treats this like an איסור כרת. Issur Karet. וולדה
פסול, V'Valdah Passul, the child is invalid. היא פסולה למאן? Hi Pesula
L'man? Who is she invalid according to Rabbi Akiva that treats this
like an איסור כרת? Issur Karet? אילימא לקהל, Ileima L'Kahal,
if it's to other Jews, משום דזניה אסרה לה לקהל, Mishum De'Zanya
Assra Lah L'Kahal, because she did a forbidden act of sex, she
now can't marry another Jew? What, is she like a ממזר? Mamzer?
You only get a ממזר, Mamzer, it's only an offspring. אלא לאו
לכהונה. Ela Lav L'Kehunah.
No, when Rabbi Akiva says she's invalid, means she's invalid for כהנים,
Kohanim, either to marry כהנים, Kohanim, which she probably wasn't anyway, or
to eat
תרומה. Terumah. So her invalidity relates to her status in the כהונה
Kehunah world. But when it says ולדה פסול Valdah Passul according to
Rabbi Akiva, למאן? L'man? Who's that go like? אילימא לכהונה, Ileima L'Kehunah,
if it's for כהונה, Kehunah, לקהל כשר? L'Kahal Kasher? What,
so you think the kid is okay to marry another Jew? והאמר
רבי עקיבא הולד ממזר? V'Ha'Amar Rabbi Akiva Ha'Valad Mamzer? We're talking about
Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva says הולד ממזר, Ha'Valad Mamzer, the child is
a ממזר. Mamzer. אלא פשיטא לקהל. Ela Peshita L'Kahal.
So when Rabbi Akiva says the child is פסול, Passul, when it
says she's פסול, Passul, it means for כהנים, Kohanim, because she'll never
be a ממזר. Mamzer. When it says the child is פסול, Passul,
we know Rabbi Akiva says it means the child is a ממזר.
Mamzer. And so therefore clearly by her we're talking about כהנים, Kohanim,
by the kid we're talking about being a ממזר. Mamzer. ומדרישא הא
כדאיתא והא כדאיתא, U'mi'reisha Ha Kide'ita V'ha Kide'ita, the same way the
beginning each one is in its own context, her question is about
כהונה, Kehunah, the kid's question is about a ממזר, Mamzer, סיפא נמי
הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא, Seifa Nami Ha Kide'ita V'ha Kide'ita, the end
also each one is in its own context, and the kid might
already, might just not be a ממזר, Mamzer, but nobody is saying
the kid is כשר לכהונה. Kasher L'Kehunah. Now how about the other
argument we had that the kid should be כשר לכהונה Kasher L'Kehunah
because it says only היא תועבה, Hi Toeva, she is a
תועבה, Toeva, and you'll say the kids are not problematic? No, I'll
give you another דרשה. Derasha. היא תועבה ואין צרתה תועבה, Hi Toeva
V'ein Tzartah Toeva, that this status applies only to her, not to
a
צרה. Tzarah. אבל בניה, Aval Baneha, children that result from this prohibition
of this איסור לאו Issur Lav of מחזיר גרושתו, Machzir Grushato, תועבים.
Toevim. Maybe they are also disqualified, at least for כהונה. Kehunah. Okay,
so we have your proof from the ברייתא Braita is not a
proof, the proof from the פסוק Pasuk is not a proof. But
let's get back to your basic argument. Where do you get an
idea that the child should be invalidated based on the idea of
the offspring of אלמנה לכהן גדול? Almanah L'Kohen Gadol? So there, that
I'm going to question because that was a bad comparison. אלמנה קשיא,
Almanah Kashya, but your whole basis in terms of learning it out
from אלמנה, Almanah, that's problematic. מה לאלמנה שכן היא עצמה מתחללת. Mah
L'Almanah She'ken Hi Atzmah Mitchallelet. As was said, you can't prove anything
from the offspring of אלמנה וכהן גדול. Almanah V'Kohen Gadol. There the
woman becomes invalidated, so that invalidity passes on to the child. Whereas
in a case of מחזיר גרושתו Machzir Grushato the woman's status doesn't
change. And since the woman's status doesn't change because it's not an
איסור כהונה, Issur Kehunah, there's no basis of saying that the offspring
of an איסור לאו Issur Lav should affect the kid. Again, this
is, I know it seems a little technical here, but this is
a huge question. We don't have too many cases of אלמנה לכהן
גדול, Almanah L'Kohen Gadol, but believe me, we have plenty of cases
of a non-Jewish father and a Jewish mother. And the question is
even when you're out of the woods of ממזר, Mamzer, does that
also mean that you don't have to worry for כהונה? Kehunah? Do
we say the offspring of an איסור לאו, Issur Lav, the girl
is כשר Kasher or פסול לכהונה? Passul L'Kehunah? So here the גמרא
Gemara is saying is you cannot learn anything from the offspring of
like אלמנה וכהן גדול. Almanah V'Kohen Gadol. That is a specific כהונה
Kehunah problem, so the offspring, and she becomes invalid, so the offspring
also becomes invalid. But a simple offspring of an איסור לאו Issur
Lav does not become invalid with כהונה Kehunah like מחזיר גרושתו. Machzir
Gerushaso. At least you certainly haven't proven that it did, yes.
I really it's so clarifying to translate פגום Pagum as stigmatized but
my question is in English when you say something's a stigma either
it's intrinsically defective or it's defective by virtue of public perception.
But here we're not talking about perception. Here it's actually something like
ontological like it's something right in its essence of the identity.
Yeah. And so the word stigmatized doesn't help, right. But you know
but in some ways it is because the forbidden act of sex
creates some problem that then adheres to the offspring. So I think
the concept of like you know stained by the act is an
appropriate... yeah. Yeah. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So we haven't proven it and actually at this stage we're willing
to say the offspring is not a problem. אלא
אי איתמר הכי איתמר, Ella ee itmar hachi itmar, fine. If it
was said here's how it was said. אמר רב יוסף בר שמעון
ברבי, Amar Rav Yosef bar Shimon bar Rabbi, oh he has explicit
bar Rabbi, הכל מודין בבא על חייבי כריתות שהולד פגום. Hakol modin
bevah al chayvei krisos shehavlad pagum. So we're dropping the idea that
an איסור לאו Issur Lav makes the kid problematic but if you
have sex with a woman who is אסור איסור כרת Assur Issur
Kareis then the child is פגום. Pagum. Now that's pretty... pretty weak
statement because we would assume the child is a ממזר. Mamzer. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאן הכל מודין? Man hakol modin? Who's conceding?
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. We have even a narrower definition of ממזר,
Mamzer, the even narrower than the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. If it's
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, דאף על גב דאמר רבי יהושע אין ממזר
מחייבי כריתות, De'af al gav de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ein mamzer mechayvei krisos,
guess what, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says not only is the offspring
of an איסור לאו Issur Lav not a ממזר, Mamzer, the offspring
of an איסור כרת Issur Kareis is not a ממזר. Mamzer. An
איסור חייבי מיתות בית דין, Issur chayvei misos beis din, okay, which
is a much narrower category. Classic example of that would be adultery,
okay. So even though he normally says the offspring of a כרת
Kareis alone is not a ממזר, Mamzer, דממזר לא הוי, Demamzer lo
hvei, fine, he's not a ממזר Mamzer but פגום מיהא הוי, Pagum
miha hvei, at least the child is אסור Assur to... for כהונה.
Kehunah. מקל וחומר מאלמנה, Mikal vachomer me'almanah, second קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer.
ומה אלמנה לכהן גדול שאין איסורה שוה בכל בנה פגום, Umah almanah
lekohen gadol she'ein issurah shaveh bakol bnah pagum, the אלמנה Almanah
who's not... whose prohibition is not universal only applies to כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol the child is invalid. זו שאיסורה שוה בכל, Zu she'issurah
shaveh bakol, the איסור כרת, Issur Kareis, אינו דין שבנה פגום? Eino
din shebnah pagum?
Certainly the child should be invalid for כהונה. Kehunah. Now say the
same thing you know in that the first case makes the woman
herself problematic. וכי תימא מה לאלמנה שכן היא עצמה נתחללה? Vechi seima
mah le'almanah sheken hi atzmah nischallelah? No by the אלמנה Almanah she
herself through that act of sex becomes... becomes you know...
problematized, becomes a חללה. Challalah. הכא נמי. Hacha nami. No there so
the same is true since we're talking about an איסור כרת, Issur
Kareis, guess what, a woman who engages in an act of sex
of איסור כרת Issur Kareis even if it's not a unique... a
unique prohibition to כהנים Kohanim but an איסור כרת Issur Kareis does
make the woman forbidden to כהנים. Kohanim. כיון שבעלה, Keivan sheba'alah,
once the man had sex with this woman, עשאה זונה, Asa'ah zonah,
turns her into this category of a זונה Zonah which is one
of the forbidden categories of כהנים. Kohanim. So basically what we can
say is when the act of sex makes the woman אסור Assur
to כהן, Kohen, that stigma or whatever status transfers to the child.
When do we have that? Any act that is a woman is...
is uniquely a כהן Kohen forbidden sex... act of sex like אלמנה
Almanah for כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, she becomes forbidden and the child
becomes forbidden. Another thing that makes her forbidden to כהנים Kohanim is
an איסור כרת. Issur Kareis. So if the woman engages in a
prohibition of an איסור כרת, Issur Kareis, I don't know, you know,
case of a wife's sister let's say, so because it's an איסור
כרת Issur Kareis it's so weighty it makes her invalid to כהנים
Kohanim and therefore that will transfer to the kid. That's if you
don't already have the kid as a ממזר. Mamzer. But we who
say in that case the kid is a ממזר, Mamzer, there's yet
to be a category of a kid that's not a ממזר Mamzer
and would still be a problem. Because if it's just... because for
us איסור כרת Issur Kareis produces a ממזר. Mamzer. איסור לאו, Issur
Lav, the woman's status doesn't change and if the woman's status doesn't
change we're arguing the kid's status will not change either, okay, so
that's where we are still that the offspring of an איסור לאו
Issur Lav the child is not a problem. Very important. Let's keep
on going. אמר רבא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן. הכל מודין.
Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan hakol modin, Now we get to the really relevant issue.
I mean מחזיר גרושתו Machzir Gerushaso does happen from time to time
but now we get to the really relevant question. אמר רבא בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan. הכל מודין, Hakol modin. everybody agrees, שעבד ועובד כוכבים, She'eved ve'oved
kochavim, a slave and a non-Jew, הבא על בת ישראל Habah al
bas Yisrael that had sex with a Jewish woman, שהולד ממזר. Shehavlad
mamzer. Now before we even get to איסור כהונה Issur Kehunah you
might remember this from a while ago, the idea that the kid
would be a ממזר Mamzer just from a non-Jewish father. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara says מאן הכל מודין? Man hakol modin? Who's this
everyone? שמעון התימני. Shimon HaTeimani. שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani דאף על גב
דאמר שמעון התימני אין ממזר מחייבי לאוין, De'af al gav de'amar Shimon
HaTeimani ein mamzer mechayvei lavin, although normally he says no ממזר Mamzer
when there's no... when it's only an איסור לאו, Issur Lav, a
negative prohibition, it would have to be an איסור כרת, Issur Kareis,
and sex with a non-Jew or slave. is not an איסור כרת
issur kareis *issur kares*, it's only an איסור לאו *issur lav*. הני
מילי *Hani mili*, that's true, says the גמרא *Gemara*, top of מה
עמוד א *mem-hey amud aleph*, מחייבי לאוין דתפסי בהו קידושין kiddushin *me-chayavei
lavin d'tafsi bu kidushin*. Normal איסור לאו *issur lav*s because as we
said before, a normal איסור לאו *issur lav*, the קידושין kiddushin *kidushin*
would be binding and you would need a גט *get*, right? Remember,
what goes—normally these things come as a package. An איסור כרת issur
kareis. *issur kares* produces a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*, and if the woman
is an איסור כרת issur kareis, *issur kares*, the קידושין *kidushin* isn't
binding. A man gives a ring to his sister and says הרי
את מקודשת לי בטבעת זו *harei at mekudeshes li b'tabaat zu*, she
doesn't need a גט *get*. Those three go together. For רבי Rebbe
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, it's an איסור לאו *issur lav* produces a ממזר
mamzer *mamzer*, and an איסור לאו *issur lav* prevents the marriage from
being binding. So the marriage not binding and the child being a
ממזר mamzer. *mamzer* are pack—usually go together. For רבי Rebbe, עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* when it's an איסור לאו *issur lav* and for שמעון התימני
*Shimon Ha-Timani* when it's an איסור כרת kareis, *issur kares*. Here by
the non-Jew we have a split, okay? On the one hand the
marriage with a non-Jew is not binding. So what's the story? Will
the kid be a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*? Until now we've been saying
on the one hand it's an איסור לאו *issur lav*, it's not
an איסור כרת kareis, *issur kares*, but the marriage isn't binding. So
what's the story with a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer*? Will that follow the
idea that the marriage isn't binding and the kid'll be a ממזר
mamzer *mamzer*? Or follow the idea that it's only a לאו *lav*
and the kid won't be a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer*? That's the גמרא's
*Gemara's* question. You could understand the logic. If marriage isn't binding and
it's completely irrelevant the marriage, then maybe that's the definition of a
ממזר mamzer *mamzer*, a type of a union in which marriage cannot
even be binding. Maybe it's not the question of לאו *lav* or
כרת *kares*, maybe it's the question of is the marriage binding. So
let's take a look. אבל הכא *Aval hacha*, in this case, עובד
כוכבים ועבד *oveid kochavim v'eved*, כיון דלא תפסי בהו קידושין *keivan d'lo
tafsi bu kidushin*, since the marriage isn't binding, כחייבי כריתות דמי *k'chayavei
krisos dami*, it's like a חייבי כריתות *chayavei krisos* and therefore maybe
the kid will be a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer*. And I'll tell you
what, you have a case of the reverse. You have a case
of an איסור כרת *issur kares* where the marriage is binding, where
the kid isn't a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*. Can anybody think of that?
Where's a case of a sexual act that is an איסור כרת
*issur kares* in the context of a binding marriage that the kid
is not a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer*?
It's נדה *niddah*.
נדה *niddah*, right? So look at that. So you have a case
where כרת *kares* does not produce a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer* because the
marriage is binding. So maybe we should say the reverse is also
true, where the marriage isn't binding even though it's not כרת *kares*,
like the case of a non-Jew, maybe the kid is a ממזר
mamzer, *mamzer*. Maybe the ממזר *mamzer* status is not about whether it's
לאו *lav* or כרת *kares*, maybe the ממזר *mamzer* status is whether
it's about whether the marriage is binding or not. And if that's
true with a non-Jew the kid would be a ממזר *mamzer*.
Just as the case of a נדה *niddah* in which the woman
was a נדה *niddah* she had a child, right?
With her husband. It isn't... the kid isn't a ממזר *mamzer*.
And that's probably most Jews, right?
So you see that the איסור כרת *issur kares*, you see that
the איסור כרת *issur kares* is not what defines... right, it doesn't
necessarily mean, let me rephrase it, איסור כרת *issur kares* doesn't necessarily
mean that the kid is a ממזר *mamzer*. So maybe it's not
about the איסור כרת *issur kares* at all, maybe it's only about
whether the marriage is binding. And therefore the case of a non-Jew,
maybe the kid would be a ממזר *mamzer*. Luckily we don't פוסק
*pasken* this way, but it's a very... it's a reasonable argument. So
let's see what—we don't
פוסק *pasken* the other way either, right?
In other words, right, we basically פוסק *pasken* לקולא *l'chula* in both
ways. That the offspring of an איסור נדה *issur niddah* is not
a ממזר *mamzer* and that the offspring of a Jewish woman and
a non-Jew is also not a ממזר *mamzer*. That you need both.
You need the marriage not to be binding and you need it
to be an איסור כרת *issur kares*. But here we're saying let's
just focus on the marriage not being binding. And therefore or not
the potential for it to be binding, right? It doesn't matter whether
there actually was מעשה קידושין *maaseh kidushin*, but it's not even potentially
binding in this case would they try to get married. So maybe
the kid is a ממזר *mamzer*. Okay, so that's a very reasonable
argument, luckily we don't rule it that way, but it's a reasonable
argument. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this, מיתיבי *Meisivei*, asked on
this, עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל *Oveid kochavim v'eved ha-ba
al bas Yisrael*, we have a ברייתא braisa *braisa*, a non-Jew or
a slave who has sex with a Jewish woman, הולד ממזר *ha-vlad
mamzer*. רבי Rebbe, שמעון בן יהודה אומר אין ממזר אלא ממי שאיסורו
איסור ערווה וענוש כרת *Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer ein mamzer ela
mi-she-issuro issur ervah v'onush kares*. No, ממזר
*mamzer* is only when it's a sexually forbidden act that is punishable
by כרת *kares*, not by... with a non-Jew. So you see, and
the גמרא *Gemara* presumably says that that is consistent with שמעון התימני
*Shimon Ha-Timani*, with שמעון התימני *Shimon Ha-Timani*. So the גמרא *Gemara*, although
it's a very reasonable position, rejects it. No, sex with a non-Jew
does not produce a ממזר *mamzer*. Thank God. So now we have
to get to question number two. Maybe though it does produce a
woman who's אסורה לכהונה *asura l'kehuna*. Okay, אלא אמר רב יוסף Amar
Rav Yosef, מאן דכולי מודי רבי Rebbe *Ela amar Rav Yosef man
d'chula modei Rabbi*. רבי Rebbe, *Rabbi* concedes. אף על גב דרבי אומר
אין הדברים הללו אמורים אלא לדברי רבי Rebbe עקיבא *Af-al-gav d'Rabbi omer
ein ha-devarim ha-lalu amurim ela l'divrei Rabbi Akiva*. Although רבי *Rabbi* says
in another context—I'm not going to get into the specifics, but he
says the thing I just said is only according to רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* who would say a חלוצה *chaluza* is like an ערווה
*ervah* and an איסור לאו *issur lav* is as bad as an
איסור כרת *issur kares*, etc., but he doesn't hold that way. He
holds like שמעון התימני *Shimon Ha-Timani* that only and that ממזר *mamzer*
and so on is only by an איסור כרת *issur kares*. Nevertheless,
באובד כוכבים ועבד מודה *b'oveid kochavim v'eved modei*.
Maybe he would agree. Although רבי שמעון בן יהודה said that you
don't have a ממזר from an עבד eved and a non-Jew, maybe
רבי would say you would? Okay, so we're not giving up yet
on that idea. We're still saying it's possible to say in general
a ממזר only from an איסור כרת and to still say, however,
with a non-Jew that also's a ממזר. And even if we have
a ברייתא that says not that way, we're going to say that
רבי, רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehudah HaNasi says that way, that maybe
a non-Jew does create a ממזר even though it's not an איסור
כרת. Let's take a look. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יצחק
בר אבדימי משום רבינו Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar
Avdimi mishum Rabbeinu in the name of רבי, רבינו, Rabbeinu, רבי יהודה
הנשיא, Rabbi Yehudah HaNasi, עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד
ממזר. Oved kochavim ve'eved haba al bas Yisrael havlad mamzer.
So we actually have an opinion of רבי that says normally you
go by איסור כרת, but when it comes to the child with
a non-Jewish man, the child is a ממזר. Okay, we'll do one
other thing about this just so you shouldn't end with that opinion.
רבי אחא שר הבירה ורבי תנחום בריה דרבי חייא איש כפר עכו,
Rabbi Acha Sar HaBirah veRabbi Tanchum breih deRabbi Chiya ish Kfar Akko,
two interesting people, רבי אחא שר הבירה, Rabbi Acha Sar HaBirah, I
don't know what that means, officer of the whatever castle, and רבי
תנחום Rabbi Tanchum the son of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya from עכו,
Akko, פרקו הנך שבייתא. parako hanech shavyasa.
They redeemed certain captive women דאתו מארמון לטבריא de'asu me'Armon leTeverya that
were coming from ארמון Armon to Tiberias. הוי חדא דאיעברא מעובד כוכבים,
Havi chada de'ibra me'oved kochavim,
one of these captive women had become pregnant through a non-Jew. ואתו
לקמיה דרבי אמי, Ve'asu lekamei deRabbi Ami,
and they came to רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said to them, רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, Rabbi Yochanan veRabbi Elazar,
so the question is what's going to be the status of the
child? Will the child be a ממזר or not? Like she was
raped, but that doesn't matter for this question, right? Offspring of a
Jewish woman and a non-Jew, what's the status of the kid? ואתו
לקמיה דרבי אמי אמר להו רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר ורבי חנינא דאמרי,
Ve'asu lekamei deRabbi Ami amar lehu Rabbi Yochanan veRabbi Elazar veRabbi Chanina
de'amri, these three rabbis, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina all say, עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על
בת ישראל הולד ממזר, oved kochavim ve'eved haba al bas Yisrael havlad
mamzer, the kid is a ממזר. So although we normally go by
כרת, here we have a serious
group of rabbis that say that fine, but with a non-Jew the
קידושין would not be binding, the child is a ממזר regardless. אמר
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef so רב Rav יוסף said to this, רבותא
למחשב גברי? Ravusa lemecheshav gavrei? What,
you think it's a big deal to make a list of how
many rabbis say that? I'll give you another list. רב ושמואל בבבל
ורבי יהושע בן לוי ובר קפרא בארץ ישראל, Rav uShmuel beVavel veRabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi uBar Kappara be'Eretz Yisrael, I have רב and שמואל
Shmuel in בבל Bavel and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi
and בר קפרא Bar Kappara in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. You have
three, I'm going to get four. רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi and בר קפרא Bar Kappara in Israel. דאמרי להו, De'amri
lehu, ואיתימא בר קפרא ואיתימא זקני דרום, ve'isima Bar Kappara ve'isima ziknei
darom, some say take out בר קפרא Bar Kappara and put in
the זקני דרום. ziknei darom. So I got four rabbis, you got
three authorities. I got four rabbis, right, more, there's זקני דרום ziknei
darom דאמרי, de'amri, עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד
כשר, oved kochavim ve'eved haba al bas Yisrael havlad kasher, that the
child is כשר. kasher. Okay, so we end with the אלא אמר
רב יוסף רבי היא, ella amar Rav Yosef Rebbe hi,
it is רבי, דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי
משום רבינו אמרו עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד ממזר.
dechi ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avdimi mishum Rabbeinu amru
oved kochavim ve'eved haba al bas Yisrael havlad mamzer. So no, now
although we have three against four or whatever, there still is the
position of רבי that says the kid is a ממזר. So we
are now going to end here in the middle of this exciting
debate, which is highly relevant, which is what is the status of
a child born from a non-Jewish father? And now we're debating whether
the child is a ממזר or not, even though normally we go
by כרת, here no קידושין is possible, so it's possible the child
is a ממזר. What we're going to look at tomorrow is even
if you conclude the child isn't a ממזר, what's the status of
the child for כהונה? kehunah? Also a very because obviously we are
going to conclude that the child is not a ממזר, but the
question of the child for כהונה kehunah is a very relevant question
which we're going to look at tomorrow, just not with me. Okay,
yes, they say.